Albany Student Press Records; Records ua809.001 ua809.001
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Albany Student Press Records
1967-1999
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
State University of New York at Albany
ua809.001
1.17 cubic ft. 19
Comprised mainly of photographs documenting students, faculty, and campus events, as well as administrative papers relating to the organization's independence from the Student Association, the Albany Student Press Records offer a glimpse into the newspaper's activities from the late 1960s to 1990s.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Web Archives
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted with the exception of one flat-file.
Acquisition Information
The Albany Student Press transferred these records to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives in 2014.
Organizational Sketch
The Albany Student Press ( ASP ), the university's student newspaper since 1964, covers campus activities, events, sports, and other topics relating to student life at the University at Albany (formerly the State University of New York at Albany). Though originally funded by the Student Association, in 1976 the ASP took its first steps toward becoming an independent organization. The ASP later registered as a not-for-profit corporation, and since 1977, the Albany Student Press Corporation has been the paper's official publisher. Commenting on this development, the editorial from the January 28th, 1977 issue notes, "As a truly separate institution at SUNYA, the ASP will be afforded the liberty to objectively report on, scrutinize and serve the university community."
While the focus of Albany's student newspaper has not changed significantly over the years, it has not always been known as the Albany Student Press. From 1916 to 1963, the paper was titled State College News and prior to the ASP 's first issue on February 14, 1964, it was briefly known as State University News.
In addition to its coverage of SUNY-related news, regular features include opinion pieces on local and national issues, movie and music reviews, and student perspectives on various subjects. For several years beginning in 1974, the ASP also included a magazine section devoted to arts and culture. Initially titled ASP Perspectives but later shortened to ASPects, the magazine was a monthly publication during the Fall semester of 1975 before merging with the weekly arts section the following year.
Scope and Contents
The Albany Student Press Records include photographs of students, faculty, guest speakers, buildings and offices, clubs and events, and other subjects relating to articles the ASP published over the years. A number of photographs document student activism and protests on campus and elsewhere. Photographs of Albany's Telethon, a student-organized event that raised money for children's organizations in the Capital Region, also take up a substantial portion of the records. State and local government officials, community events, and various institutions around Albany are also represented, but account for a smaller portion of the records. While the images date from the late 1960s to 1990s, the majority were taken in the 1970s and 1980s.
The paper records, though not as extensive, include some interesting documents showing the research and planning that went into becoming an independent student newspaper. Additional documents of note, including blueprints, correspondence, and applications, pertain to the ASP 's offices on the third floor of the Campus Center.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1 - Images, 1967-1996, Undated
Series 2 - Administrative, 1971-1999, Undated
Both series are arranged alphabetically by subject.
College student newspapers and periodicals; Black-and-white photographs; Bylaws (administrative records); Memorandums; Floor plans; Web Archives; Digital Files; UAlbany Student Groups; Albany Student Press Corp.; State University of New York at Albany
- Images, 1967-1996; Undated; 1
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  Series 1 is comprised almost entirely of photographs taken by the University Photo Service, a separate student organization that has supplied much of the ASP 's photography over the years. However, some photographs may have been taken by ASP staff. Additionally, a small number of images originate from other sources, including the Associated Press, College Press Service, and Liberation News Service. A single illustration, noted in the container list below, is also included. While many of these images appeared in issues of the ASP, others may never have been published.
  Most of the photographs are in black and white, though a few are in color. Information about each image varies; the name of the photographer, the year the photograph was taken, and the subject depicted are noted on the back of many, but several have no such identifying information. The size and condition of each photograph also varies from folder to folder.
  In most cases, original folder titles were retained. By and large, the titles reflect the general subject of the items contained within. New titles were created in cases where labels were missing or misleading. There were also a number of loose photographs that had to be sorted into related folders.
  - Affirmative Action Dept., 1980; 1984; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 1)
  - Afro-American Studies, 1971; 1984; 1986; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 2)
  - Airplanes, 1983; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 3)
  - Albany Mayor, Officials, 1974-1975; 1980 (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 4)
  - Albany State University Black Alliance (ASUBA), 1993-1995 (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 5)
  - Alumni Quad, House, 1983; 1987; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 6)
  - Anthropology Staff, 1986-1987; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 7)
  - AP Photos (General), 1984-1985 (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 8)
  - Art and Architecture, 1968; 1971-1972; 1975; 1983; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 9)
  - ASP Staff, 1975; 1985-1986; Undated; 1.34 MB (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 10)
  - Atmospheric Sciences, 1982; 1984; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 11)
  - Banks, 1971; 1981; 1983; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 12)
  - Board of Trustees, 1982; 1984; 1986-1987; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 13)
  - Buses, 1979; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 14)
  - Dining, Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 15)
  - Groups, Clubs, Events, 1975; 1985-1989; 1994; 1996; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 16)
  - Holidays, 1967; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 17)
  - Homecoming, 1986-1987; 1994-1996 (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 18)
  - Hotel Wellington, 1988 (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 19)
  - Larkfest, 1982; 1984; 1987; 1991; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 20)
  - Musicians, 1983; 1986-1987; 1995; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 21)
  - Offices on Campus, 1971-1972; 1975; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 22)
  - PAC Center, 1980; 1986; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 23)
  - Parking, 1986-1987 (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 24)
  - Philosophy, 1980; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 25)
  - Phunky Phil Photos, Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 26)
  - Podium Events, 1984; 1986-1987; 1991; 1995-1996; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 27)
  - Podium Shots, 1982; 1986; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 28)
  - Poli Sci Faculty, 1970; 1972; 1975; 1980-1982; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 29)
  - Protests, 1967-1989; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 30)
  - Psychology, Sociology staff, 1976; 1980; 1982; 1984; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 31)
  - Public Speaking Shots, 1970-1988; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 32)
  - Quad Boards, 1986 (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 33)
  - SA Lawyers, 1971; 1980-1981; 1986; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 34)
  - SA Minority Affairs, 1986-1987; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 35)
  - SA Off-campus Assoc., 1984-1985 (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 36)
  - SA Supreme Court, 1986-1988 (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 37)
  - SA Vice President, 1984; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 38)
  - SASU [Student Association of the State University of New York], 1985; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 39)
  - Senior Week, 1987 (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 40)
  - Speakers' Forum staff, 1981; 1983-1984; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 41)
  - Speakers on Campus, 1982; 1984; 1986; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 42)
  - Speakers, Activists, 1983-1984; 1986; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 43)
  - Sports Illustrations, Graphics, Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 44)
  - Sports, 1983-1984; 1987; 1994; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 45)
  - State and Local Government, 1981-1984; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 46)
  - State Education Dept., 1975 (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 47)
  - SUNYA Architecture (uptown), 1972; 1975; 1984-1987; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 48)
  - Telephones, 1984; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 49)
  - Telethon, 1967-1987; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 50)
  - Tunnels, 1972; 1985; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 51)
  - Univ. Cinemas, 1986; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 52)
  - Univ. Concert Board, 1980-1981; 1983-1984; 1985-1986; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 53)
  - Univ. Council, 1980; 1984-1985; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 54)
  - Univ. Police, staff, 1971-1983; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 55)
  - Univ. Presidents, 1994; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 56)
  - Univ. Senate, Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 57)
  - Uptown Quads, 1972; 1985-1987; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 58)
  - US Government, 1984 (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 59)
  - Various SA Folks, 1986; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 60)
  - Vending Machines, 1984; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 61)
  - Video Game Room, Games, 1982; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 62)
  - Voting, 1982-1985; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 63)
  - VP for Academic Planning and Development, Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 64)
  - VP for Finance and Business staff, 1971; 1979; 1984; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 65)
  - VP for Student Affairs staff, 1970; 1976; 1983-1984; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 66)
  - VP for University Affairs, 1984; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 67)
  - WCDB 91 FM, 1982-1983; 1986; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 68)
  - Women's Studies, 1984-1986 (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 69)
  - World Week, 1983; 1986 (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 70)
  - Writer's Institute, 1984-1985; Undated (Box 1 (1-Images), Folder 71)
- Administrative, 1971-1999; Undated; 2
  Series 2 primarily consists of records pertaining to structural and organizational changes at the ASP in the late 1970s. Several records, including memoranda from Editor-in-Chief Stephen Dzinanka and Managing Editor Spence Raggio, relate to the ASP 's transition to an independent organization. Applications, correspondence, and blueprints relating to space allocations and proposed office alterations can be found in the "Space" folder. Most of the blueprints are oversized items and stored in separate flat files. Additional contents of note include: by-laws of the Albany Student Press Corporation, the ASP 's constitution, a contract between the ASP and the University Photo Service, and general accident insurance policies.
  - General Correspondence, 1999; Undated (Box 2 (2-Administrative), Folder 1)
  - Independence, 1969; 1976-1979; 1981; 1986-1987; Undated (Box 2 (2-Administrative), Folder 2)
  - Insurance Paperwork, 1991-1992 (Box 2 (2-Administrative), Folder 3)
  - Space, 1971; 1975; 1977-1980; 1990; Undated (Box 2 (2-Administrative), Folder 4)
  - Space [RESTRICTED], 1978; Undated (Flat-file 1)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Must consult archivist before viewing this material.
  - Space, 1979 (Flat-file 2)
  - Student Association - Election Regulations, 1993; Undated (Box 2 (2-Administrative), Folder 5)
  - University Photo Service Contract, Undated (Box 2 (2-Administrative), Folder 6)
- Web Archives, 2013 February 15-2016 September 28; 3; 294 captures
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Web crawling is managed through the Internet Archive's Archive-It service. This page includes links to both the university's collection and the Internet Archive's public collection.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Web Archives
  - http://www.albanystudentpress.net/ - University Archives collection, 2015 October 7-2016 September 28 (Web-archive 1)
  - WARC file for http://www.albanystudentpress.net/, (please see https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Web_ARChive for more details), 2015 October 7-2016 September 28 (Warc 1)
    WARC files are very large and difficult to work with. Your request may take time to process, and we may be unable to deliver your request remotely. Please consult an archivist if you are interested in researching with web archives.
  - http://www.albanystudentpress.net/ - Internet Archive collection, 2013 February 15-2016 September 28 (Web-archive 2)